LabLog
 -----------------------------------
1/25/18

Downloaded HMM models for pVOG
Downloaded HMM3.1b2
	.exes are in the binaries folder
Completed test case
	1. Flaten profiles
		cat $(ls AllvogHMMprofiles/VOG04*) > testDataBase
	2. Compress database
		./hmmer-3.1b2-linux-intel-x86_64/binaries/hmmpress testDataBase 
	3. Search 
		 ./hmmer-3.1b2-linux-intel-x86_64/binaries/hmmscan testDataBase sequence.fasta
		 
		 
Test case was NP_049803.1 which belongs to VOG0474

Output:


	# hmmscan :: search sequence(s) against a profile database
# HMMER 3.1b2 (February 2015); http://hmmer.org/
# Copyright (C) 2015 Howard Hughes Medical Institute.
# Freely distributed under the GNU General Public License (GPLv3).
# - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -
# query sequence file:             sequence.fasta
# target HMM database:             testDataBase
# - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -

Query:       NP_049803.1  [L=391]
Description: gp27 baseplate hub subunit [Enterobacteria phage T4]
Scores for complete sequence (score includes all domains):
   --- full sequence ---   --- best 1 domain ---    -#dom-
    E-value  score  bias    E-value  score  bias    exp  N  Model    Description
    ------- ------ -----    ------- ------ -----   ---- --  -------- -----------
   8.2e-205  672.6   7.5   9.4e-205  672.4   7.5    1.0  1  VOG0474   


Domain annotation for each model (and alignments):
>> VOG0474  
   #    score  bias  c-Evalue  i-Evalue hmmfrom  hmm to    alifrom  ali to    envfrom  env to     acc
 ---   ------ ----- --------- --------- ------- -------    ------- -------    ------- -------    ----
   1 !  672.4   7.5  1.1e-206  9.4e-205       1     384 [.       1     385 [.       1     386 [. 1.00

  Alignments for each domain:
  == domain 1  score: 672.4 bits;  conditional E-value: 1.1e-206
      VOG0474   1 mkvlqragypNvsiklyedYdawkenrfveLaatfttltlrdglyGrneglLqfyDaknlhtklnGeeiiQiSlanant.kkvetriYgvkhssvsvd 97 
                  m++lqr+gypN+s+kl+++Ydaw++nrfveLaat+ttlt+rd+lyGrneg+LqfyD+kn+htk++G+eiiQiS+anan+ ++v+triYg+kh+svsvd
  NP_049803.1   1 MSMLQRPGYPNLSVKLFDSYDAWSNNRFVELAATITTLTMRDSLYGRNEGMLQFYDSKNIHTKMDGNEIIQISVANANDiNNVKTRIYGCKHFSVSVD 98 
                  789*********************************************************************************************** PP

      VOG0474  98 skgdniialnLepihkvenlkfsrsffnnavesikemirviYkdkkllaptieginvyvPrvpwvstiedyldyvrevglsvesekfvfvweDisGik 195
                  skgdniia++L++ih++enlkf+r ff++a esikem++viY+d++ll+p+i++in+yvP++pw+st+e+yl+yvrev+l+v s+kfvfvw+Di+G++
  NP_049803.1  99 SKGDNIIAIELGTIHSIENLKFGRPFFPDAGESIKEMLGVIYQDRTLLTPAINAINAYVPDIPWTSTFENYLSYVREVALAVGSDKFVFVWQDIMGVN 196
                  ************************************************************************************************** PP

      VOG0474 196 lkdyeslikqepiklvvgeprligefvqelesplaydfewltkanqltrnplenatlyshsfldkeldrittgegensivvsrsgaysdmtyrngyee 293
                  ++dy+++i+qep++++vgep+lig+f+qel++playdf wltk+n ++r+p++nat+y+hsfld+++++ittg+gensivvsrsgays+mtyrngyee
  NP_049803.1 197 MMDYDMMINQEPYPMIVGEPSLIGQFIQELKYPLAYDFVWLTKSNPHKRDPMKNATIYAHSFLDSSIPMITTGKGENSIVVSRSGAYSEMTYRNGYEE 294
                  ************************************************************************************************** PP

      VOG0474 294 airlltmaqydgyakcktvGnfeltpGvkiefgdeknqfktdfyvdeviheisnnssitnlymftngkelkpvelvkvknelksdttakes 384
                  airl+tmaqydgyakc+t+Gnf+ltpGvki+f+d+knqfkt+fyvdevihe+snn+s+t+lymftn+++l+++++vkvkne+ksdtt++es
  NP_049803.1 295 AIRLQTMAQYDGYAKCSTIGNFNLTPGVKIIFNDSKNQFKTEFYVDEVIHELSNNNSVTHLYMFTNATKLETIDPVKVKNEFKSDTTTEES 385
                  ***************************************************************************************9986 PP



Internal pipeline statistics summary:
-------------------------------------
Query sequence(s):                         1  (391 residues searched)
Target model(s):                          83  (15867 nodes)
Passed MSV filter:                         4  (0.0481928); expected 1.7 (0.02)
Passed bias filter:                        1  (0.0120482); expected 1.7 (0.02)
Passed Vit filter:                         1  (0.0120482); expected 0.1 (0.001)
Passed Fwd filter:                         1  (0.0120482); expected 0.0 (1e-05)
Initial search space (Z):                 83  [actual number of targets]
Domain search space  (domZ):               1  [number of targets reported over threshold]
# CPU time: 0.03u 0.01s 00:00:00.04 Elapsed: 00:00:00.03
# Mc/sec: 206.80
//
[ok]

-------------------------------------------------------
1/29/18

hmmscan: hmmscan is used to search protein sequences against collections of protein proﬁles. For each sequence in <seqﬁle>, 
use that query sequence to search the target database of proﬁles in <hmmdb>, and output ranked lists of the proﬁles with 
the most signiﬁcant matches to the sequence. The <seqﬁle> may contain more than one query sequence. It can be in FASTA format
, or several other common sequence ﬁle formats (genbank, embl, and uniprot, among others), or in alignment ﬁle formats 
(stockholm, aligned fasta, and others). See the --qformat option for a complete list. The <hmmdb> needs to be press’ed using hmmpress
 before it can be searched with hmmscan. This creates four binary ﬁles, sufﬁxed .h3{ﬁmp}. The query <seqﬁle> may be ’-’ (a dash character), 
in which case the query sequences are read from a <stdin> pipe instead of from a ﬁle. The <hmmdb> cannot be read from a <stdin> stream, because
 it needs to have those four auxiliary binary ﬁles generated by hmmpress. The output format is designed to be human-readable, but is often so
 voluminous that reading it is impractical, and parsing it is a pain. The --tblout and --domtblout options save output in simple tabular 
formats that are concise and easier to parse. The-o option allows redirecting the mai noutput, including throwing it away in /dev/null.

Testing tabular output

output:

                                                               --- full sequence ---- --- best 1 domain ---- --- domain number estimation ----
# target name        accession  query name           accession    E-value  score  bias   E-value  score  bias   exp reg clu  ov env dom rep inc description of target
#------------------- ---------- -------------------- ---------- --------- ------ ----- --------- ------ -----   --- --- --- --- --- --- --- --- ---------------------
VOG0474              -          NP_049803.1          -           8.2e-205  672.6   7.5  9.4e-205  672.4   7.5   1.0   1   0   0   1   1   1   1 -
#
# Program:         hmmscan
# Version:         3.1b2 (February 2015)
# Pipeline mode:   SCAN
# Query file:      sequence.fasta
# Target file:     testDataBase
# Option settings: ./hmmer-3.1b2-linux-intel-x86_64/binaries/hmmscan --tblout test.log testDataBase sequence.fasta 
# Current dir:     /home/stancliffe/pVOG
# Date:            Mon Jan 29 11:21:33 2018
# [ok]


possible reporting parameters are found on pg 71 of the manual

Deleted local copy of install
Full files can be found in in /local/vol00/shared/bin/

added to path

new command:
hmmscan --tblout test.log  testDataBase sequence.fasta 
	searches testDataBase for the sequence in sequence.fasta
	uses tabular output


LOOKING UP HHPRED

includes structure prediction, more sensitive


Making compete database

need to remove old database files
	rm testDataBase*
Flatten:
	 cat $(ls AllvogHMMprofiles/*) > testDataBase 
Compress:
	 hmmpress testDataBase  
Search: 
	hmmscan --tblout test.log  testDataBase sequence.fasta 

Viral quotient is the percentage of genomes in which a protein is in a the VOG

Questions: 
	For final results
	Input: Genome (or large sample) -> Annotation
	Input: Individual Sequences -> Report
	Options for score reporting
		Have options, 
		Need to curate defaults
	
	To tune parameters test self hits, make sure all the correct values are being found

tested running the entire Acaryochloris phage A-HIS1, complete genome
GenBank: FN436268.1

included in pVOG construction
in 13 VOGs

After running hmmscan with default settings 64 hits found (genome is 97 proteins), but only 13 vogs 
Made a harsher evalue of 1e-5 instead of 10, then 24 hits found. Possible that this harsher evalue is more accurate

SHOULDN"T THERE ONLY BE 13 unique vog hits? 

Question:
	Should the search be weaker or stronger than the construction?

----------------------------------------
1/30/18

Looking further into hmmscan: 
	In some cases, rather than wishing to search a single model against a collection of sequences, you may
	wish to annotate all the instances of a collection of HMMs found in a single sequence.
	In the case of proteins,
	hmmscan
	is for annotating all the different known/detectable domains in a given
	protein sequence.  It takes a single query sequence and an HMM database as input.  The HMM database
	might be Pfam, SMART, or TIGRFams, for example, or another collection of your choice.
Vs hmmsearch:
	Searching a protein sequence database with a single protein profile HMM => search each HMM against the genome and concatenate output

Meeting Notes

Bit score > 40
First biased toward false positives
2nd bias against false positives
More expensive bias toward false negative
1e-10 for evalue cutoff
Coverage threshold of 50
Ignore analogy
Homology
               Othorolog
Could build in room for expensibility
Report only good hits

hard code in reporting thresholds
limit input file to 1000 sequences per query

-----------------------------------------
1/31/18

Installed anacanda (requires no admin)
Developed unix script to run hmmscan (automates the path)

Developed python script to filter results and output those hits with bitscore > 40 and remove excess information
Need to rename and finalize hmmdatabase name   done
add funcitonality to input query name   done
figure out final output format

want to examine the relationship between thresholded and hits/queryseq

next steps: sample genomes used in pVOG construction and examine hits/query as a function of bit score

added to python script file containing the number of hits per query

need to download dataset for testing

---------------------------

2/1/18

Developed python script to parse out and protein accession numbers from AllFamilyProteinList.tsv
	Only takes those ending in .1
	and takes after the hyphen
Developed a python script that randomly samples n number of a accessions from the list
the output of this scipt can be used with batch Entrez to get FASTA file of sequences 
NOTE: number of sequences must be less than 1000
Must use chmod 755 filename to change permissions on script files

Developed analysis script to test on small data set. 

Ran total unix script to generate small sample data set n=100

Analysis script, hpqpbitScore.py, plots mean(hits/query) vs bitscore

Ideas: Extend to SD to get more complete picture with statistical rigor

Repeat for evalue thresholding to find optimal parameters

Completed analysi n = 1000 for bitscore thresholding, seems cutoff is around 37-38 with linear decrease after that see images

altered scripts to filter on evalue threshold 

completed analysis with n = 1000

similar results as before appears that the best evalue is in the neighborhood of 1e-10

--------------------------

2/7/18

Bias definition: It’s possible for profiles and/or sequences to have biased residue compositions that result in “significant”
log-odds bit scores not because the profile matches the sequence particularly well, but because the null
model matches the sequence particularly badly.

Started presentation for DK on Tuesday
Started final pipeline, still debugging maxSequences conditiion

--------------------------
2/9/18

Finished maxSequences condition and updated bash script to run the analysis
to set a variable equal to the return of a function use $(command)
feed input into python script that organizes and outputs a csv file
tab deliminter that can be inputed into excel using the data manager
	idealy could be openned directly with excel
to run ./pVOGPipeline.sh <inputFile>
-----------------------------	
2/10/18

Created new scripts to filter based on evalue or bitscore separtly.
	

Updated the analysis script to gather data

put together slides for presentation

----------------------------

2/10/18

Created scripts to automate parameter sweep for multiple input files
downloaded 10 x 1000 samples to run parameter sweep
	paramAuto.sh
started batch analysis that ran over night

---------------------------

2/12/18

Analyzed results of large scale parameter sweep. Result data can be found in HitsPerQueryEval and HitsPerQueryBS dat files. Analysis with hpqpbitScoreProcessorEVal
and BS python scripts generates plots with error bars that are the standard error (std/sqrt(n)). 

Added to scripts to looks at percentage of querys with a hit. Similar plots, curvature is reversed. Divergence instead of convergence at extrema of threshold 

Ran test on 300 queries (~2min to complete) 
started going through results  with params:
	ethresh=10e-10
	bitThresh=40
	
Found one paralog
Continueing handcuration of resonably scored entries

---------------------------

2/13/18

Meeting with DK
	Figure out how to do coverage threshold, possible hmmsearch against best hits
	Test T4 or other well known phage 
	Tab Delited vs Comma Separated
		Make it compatable with R, Excel, Perl, Python 
	Keep looking for errors 
	
Alginments
	How to algin HMM to sequence
	possibly HMMAlign
		warning that not for global alginment (maybe that is not what we need anyway)
	Testing that with sequence
	yields the following (top hit with hmmScan)
	# STOCKHOLM 1.0

#=GS ALA45955.1 DE hypothetical protein PAC5_28 [Propionibacterium phage PAC5]

ALA45955.1         ------------------MLADKTIPATQLARMLTEAGYPISATVIKDYRRKQANTTQKKEEENQ
#=GR ALA45955.1 PP ..................8********************************************98
#=GC PP_cons       ..................8********************************************98
#=GC RF            xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx
//
TRUE sequence: MLADKTIPATQLARMLTEAGYPISATVIKDYRRKQANTTQKKEEENQ

---------------------------

2/15

Updated output filter to contain any delimiter
	R csv: https://flowingdata.com/2015/02/18/loading-data-and-basic-formatting-in-r/
	Looks like it can be either
	Python pandas also can be either

Downloaded t4 genome

---------------------------

2/17/18

Ran t4 genome with bitscore 30 evalue 10e-7

Updated scripts so that the delimiter is an input into outputFilter4Pipeline.py, value is set in pVOGPipeline.sh
comma separated reads right into excel

Running the t4 genome
	looking at hits in the 30-40 range
	on the same order between 1st and 2nd hit seem to be a VOG that needs to be combined
	If 1st >> 2nd generally seems to be a false positive on the second hit
		look at mean %change in first and second hits in terms of bitscore and evlaue
	How to tell what is a good first hit? 
	Above all in the false positives?
		will eliminate some good hits
	impossible to tell
	
----------------------------
	
2/19/18

created powerpoint for meeting tomorrow

finished analysis of t4 genome
	took till bitscore > 55 for convergene
	Do I need to repeat for evalue? Seems like 10e-10 is valid
	
Possible to have a weaker second hit threshold that is determined if the first hit is greater than 6x greater than the second hit, don't included

Coverage

Using hmmalign it seems 
In the output, uppercase letters represent residues that align to a consensus position in the original alignment (corresponding to a match state in the model). Lowercase letters are used to represent inserted residues. Periods represent gaps
 A value of '0' indicates a posterior probability of between 0.0 and 0.05
 '1' indicates between 0.05 and 0.15
 '2'indicates between 0.15 and 0.25 and so on up to '9' which indicates between 0.85 and 0.95
A value of '*' indicates a posterior probability of between 0.95 and 1.0. 
Higher posterior probabilities correspond to greater confidence that the aligned residue belongs where it appears in the alignment.


Then can use this to align top hits to the VOG of choice, 
	
Repeating paramRun with new evalue of 10e-10 to see the effect of the sweep 

thinking about how to do alignment
1. All unix
	make new file during 2nd filtering of just sequenceName : VOG
	run hmmalign, use grep to pull output and find alignment length, delete that pair if not meeting threshold
	
2. All python
	read in all the sequences at the start
	During 2nd filtering, grab the hmm and the sequence, use vertibi algorithim
	remove then
3. Mixture
	Call alignment 
----------------------------
	
	
2/20/18

Meeting with DK
	Send a example output file 
	Do another manual curration of the t7 viral genome
	Look only at second hit to avoid skewing the s2n ratio
	Coverage 
		Does the info exist in hmmsearch
		How long does it take to analyze 1000 hmm calls with some data processing
		
Goals for upcoming week
	complete t7 analysis
	do trial run with hmmalign
	want coverage of > 50 of query coverage
		will need another script containing 
			accession   pVOG   
		create a splitting script 
		separates fasta into indiviual sequences, name is accession contains sequence and length of sequence (in fasta format)
		
		workthrough
		
		get fasta: split fasta
		
		run search
		
		filter4EvalBit
		
		generate accession:pVOG file
		
		for allHits in above file
			run hmmalgin
			processalignment
			(WHAT IS THE OUTPUT
	
----------------------
2/21/18

Downloaded t7 genome 60 proteins

created trainingPipeline.py which only looks at top 2 hits, and creates another file with the second hit query and target vog

started script to read that file and sequentially call hmmalign

Need to write fasta splitting script to complete this

then how to consolidate information?

add one at a time and then filter again?

For now just do the file io operation to get a idea of time. 

Wrote fasta to split named accession 
>seqLenght
sequence....


----------------------
2/22/18 

Finished testAlignmentProcessor script which returns the coverage and then is captured the hmmAlign.sh

Seems pretty quick

Next steps

formalize procedure and use it on a 1000 size

Then get results for t7

----------------------
2/23/18 		
	
	
Compiled into script called pVOGTrainingPipelinewCOV.sh

Runtime for 1000 proteins = 
real    9m10.367s
user    9m6.780s
sys     5m42.804s

Using the pVOGPipeline.sh

Runtime for 1000 proteins with coverage calculation = 
real    8m54.272s
user    8m56.808s
sys     5m36.052s

=> seems pretty reasonable

Need to determine what information it gives

started merging script to combine all the information 
	-shouldn't be much longer
	
Look over t7 genome
	on Monday
	
Finish merging script tomorrow and get the data

----------------------------------
2/26

Merging script complete 

----------------------------------
2/27

Implemented merging into pVOGTrainingPipelinewCOV script

Got the data for t7

timed again with random 1000 samples 

want to look at t4 again, interested in 40-60 range

made powerpoint for DK meeting

fixed bug in alignment processor
	sometimes alignment is many lines long
	
temp.txt needed to be deleted from environment

-------------------------------------
2/28

Run t7 and t4 through new pipeline

-------------------------------------
3/3

Reanalyzed t4 with coverage information

Analyzed t7 and lambda 

Seems that coverage does make a significant difference, data has clear threshold looking at coverage, not so with bitscore

=> filter proposed is 60% coverage and bitscore of 60

8:2 S2N 
recovers 60% of true positives

Testing on larger scale

Updated filteredResultCoverageMerger to reflect new thresholds. Have the function goodHits that can be modified. Updated pVOGpipeline = pVOGTrainingPipelinewCOV

Next Steps:
	Write abstract
	Look at individual hits
	Think about broader test





	



	
	
